hey this is Diego Ramos and after a bit
of a Hiatus involving unfortunate
illnesses for each of the journalists
for sale host we're back and with a
massive guest uh my co-host Max Jones
and I welcome former CIA analyst and uh
torture program whistleblower John
kiraku after a much needed reminder of
the history of the torture program
following the latest 911 anniversary on
the sheer intelligence podcast which
will link below uh we wanted to ask John
about the state of the media's uh
relationship with whistleblowers and
taking the case of The Intercept
controversial handling of uh multiple
whistleblower accounts as a shining
example of the eroding ethics and
competence uh of Journalism within the
United States uh John takes us through
his personal history with the media
shedding wisdom on where we're at in the
grasps of the National Security State
and uh yeah and make sure to like
comment and subscribe to help us fight
the algorithm and enjoy hi John thanks
so much for joining joining us happy to
do it thanks for inviting me of course
um so just to kind of start off maybe a
little more broadly uh I kind of just
want to get your read on the state of
the media and the First Amendment since
it's clear that the media is compromised
to an extent and there's a growing
Reliance of using the government as a
source for information about you know
really important um issues regarding war
and and and you know all all types of
very important um stuff and there's sort
of a bigger trust as well in the
government where you know you'll you'll
have Outlets exclusively relying on you
know Anonymous sources and and a
government
officials uh but in general do you feel
like the media can still be a safe haven
for whistleblowers and or should other
means of disclosing information be taken
um similar to maybe Wikileaks is a
system of anon of an anonymous Dropbox
or any sort of kind of innovative
way wow that's a that's a good good and
powerful question actually I'm glad that
you started off with it because I think
that you've cut right to the
chase so the the quick answer is um
looking at the media overall I I do not
think that the media in general can be
trusted uh especially with National
Security information um you know time
was where where you could go to the
Washington Post or the New York Times or
the Los Angeles Times and and um your
identity would be protected while your
information was being vetted and if that
information was determined to be in the
National interest it would be published
just like Daniel ellberg did or just
like um the uh the what do they what do
we call them now the the burglar did uh
with information related to the uh
Vietnam War and I'm sorry to say that we
really can't do that anymore with the
media for a variety of reasons
first of all many in the media are very
very closely tied to the intelligence
community and especially to the CIA and
the CIA is forbidden by law from
recruiting American journalists they
have been since 1975 but they do the
next best thing they cultivate
journalists by giving them proprietary
leaks um not even to say that those
leaks are necessarily true but they're
spun as being true so they have
preferred journalists that they go to uh
one that immediately comes to mind is
David Ignatius at the uh at the
Washington Post another is kend delanian
at NBC News and we can talk about him in
more uh depth later he's formerly of the
Los Angeles Times and uh you know this
the CIA will give them a story will give
them a a leak in some cases will give
them access to classified information
knowing that they're going to spin it in
a pro CIA way and get the CIA side of
the story out there that's an authorized
leak that is just as illegal as an
unauthorized leak of course but it's
never ever prosecuted because it's
official it's an official
leak as if that weren't bad enough
you've got situations like well let's
say the situation at The Intercept you
know the intercept was supposed to be
sort of a Back to Basics independent
investigative Outlet uh that was not uh
was not in the pay of any organization
that didn't owe any favors to anybody
and could be truly
independent and if anything the reverse
of that is true the the interet might be
independent maybe maybe not um I I
tweeted something a couple of years ago
and I meant it literally I said I
tweeted at the
intercept and I said something like are
you guys really that stupid or are you
in the pay of the FBI serious question I
said because in my view nobody could be
as stupid when it comes to National
Security whistleblowing as The Intercept
has been and what I mean is
this uh The Intercept has been
responsible The Intercept or or
journalists from The Intercept have been
responsible for putting five National
Security whistleblowers in prison
and I'll give you just a couple of
examples uh one was reality winner
reality winner was a a skilled linguist
at NSA she was a member of the US Air
Force and uh she believed that she had
uncovered evidence that um that Donald
Trump had been duped by the Russian
government in the runup to the 2016
election whether that was true or not is
irrelevant for this story what's
relevant was she came across a a an
analytic product written by NSA
classified at the secret level so there
were no sources and methods in it but it
was
classified she believed that it proved
that that Donald Trump had committed a
crime and her chain of command wouldn't
do anything about it so she on her own
took this document and she sent it to uh
the intercept using their encryption key
that they had on their
website now this went to two journalists
at The Intercept two journalists who
build themselves as National Security
Specialists one was Matthew Cole and the
other was Richard
Esposito um what did they do with that
classified document they immediately
emailed it back to
NSA and said hey we just received this
can you confirm that it's an actual NSA
document now if you are a national
security
journalist you would know of
course that anytime somebody from NSA
CIA FBI or a handful of other National
Security organizations prints a
document your employee identification
number is embedded in the document in
the period at the end of a sentence or
in the dot of an ey right it'll say John
kirak to 21689 91 in a period at the end
of a sentence you can't see it unless
you look at it on microscope but they
sent this document back to NSA they
immediately identified the source as
reality winner they waited until the
intercept published the piece and 40
minutes after they published the article
reality winner was under arrest and
charged with
Espionage Now The Intercept did the
exact same thing with an FBI agent from
the FBI's uh Min Minneapolis field
office he had he had come across an FBI
an internal FBI
memo uh that admitted that the FBI was
probably guilty of racism in promotions
what he did is he took out his cell
phone and he took a
photograph of the memo on his screen and
sent it to the intercept The Intercept
sent it back to the FBI hey is this an
actual FBI uh
memo they could
tell from the picture that The Intercept
had sent them that it was a photograph
of the memo taken from the screen of a
computer so what they was that the same
was were those the same journalists same
two journalists oh same two J oh wow
same two journalists Matthew Cole and
Richard Esposito so what they did was
they went back and looked at the
security camera
footage from every um
computer that had accessed the memo and
they identified FBI Agent Terry Albury
as the person who had taken the picture
and they arrested him they charged him
with Espionage and they sent him to
prison for three and a half
years now Matthew
Cole in my own case um sent me an email
one day and he
said he a dozen names I'm writing a book
about the Abu Omar rendition from Milan
it was a kidnapping that the CIA carried
out in Milan can you introduce me to any
of these 12 people so that I can
interview them for my book I said I
don't have any idea who these people are
so he sent me a second list of another
12 names and I said look you obviously
know this issue far better than I do I
never had anything to do with
kidnappings I don't know anything about
the Abu Omar
operation and he saidwell what about
this guy that you mention on page
whatever it was 125 of your book I think
his name is
John and I said oh that's John Doe I
don't know whatever happened to him he's
probably retired and living in Virginia
somewhere as it turned out Matthew
Cole was not writing a book about the
Abu Omar rendition that was a lie he was
secretly working for the Guantanamo
defense
attorneys so he took my confirmation of
John Doe's name and sent it to an
investigator for Human Rights Watch who
in turn sent it to the Guantanamo
defense attorneys who in turn put it in
a classified filing saying we've
identified a CIA officer by the name of
John Doe and we want to interview him
excuse me we want to interview him the
judge Rec recognized the fact that this
name was classified he turned it over to
the FBI and the FBI went back to Human
Rights Watch and said where'd you get
this
name and Human Rights Watch said we got
it from Matthew Cole he's one of our
investigators they went to Matthew Cole
and said where'd you get this name and
Matthew Cole said John kiraku gave it to
me so two dozen FBI agents raided my
house arrested me and charged me with
five felonies including three counts of
Espionage so you tell me are they just
that stupid or are they working with the
FBI yeah and the thing that's uh
particularly suspicious about the
reality winter case is that uh it the
documents that leaked that didn't
provide evidence that there was Russian
hacking um were also in the benefit of
the National Security State uh that was
disseminating a lot of the lies that
were were they were saying that Russia
was hacking the election and helping
Donald Trump get put into office and
then it also was in the National
Security State's interest that reality
winner goes to uh prison after that
because now you scare away anyone that
wants to ex reveal any kind of Truth so
look how many birds you've killed with
that one stone you've frightened away
any other potential
whistleblower right you have damaged The
credibility and campaign of Donald Trump
maybe and you've perpetuated the lie
that the intelligence Community wants
out there that the Russians have
successfully interfered in our
election it was perfect if you're the
CIA it was a perfect
operation and reality winner for that
that
one that momentary lapse in
judgment got five years and four months
in
prison draconian
yeah absolutely and and it leads to my
next question which is um and I think
we've I think we've kind of already
answered it but I guess I'll ask you
directly but
so it's pretty clear but I'll ask but do
you think there's an effort from the
National Security State to basically
make the
media uh you know a Minefield that's
almost impossible to navigate when you
have these institutions like The
Intercept that branded themselves on
being you know uh four whistleblowers uh
where it's a mindfield for
whistleblowers to walk through and like
you know even during ellsberg's time I
think the the New York Times kind of
betrayed him in away because they
started reporting some of the stories
that were uh smearing him but you know
when you have an institution like The
Intercept which you just laid out it's
either co-opted or it's or these guys
are just somehow the dumbest people to
ever live right um so how much worse has
it gotten and what does it say about the
goals of the National Security State
another great question thank you for
that so let me answer it in two ways
number
one
um let's talk about kend delanian in
answer to your question kend delanian
was a uh was a national security
journalist for the Los Angeles Times he
then went to NBC news as the chief
National Security journalist um for NBC
and
MSNBC okay with that in mind uh there is
another journalist for Bloomberg Jason
leapold Jason leapold is the king of the
Freedom of Information
Act uh in fact a pentagon spokesman
called him a Foya terrorist because he's
filed so many Freedom of Information Act
requests more than anybody else on earth
except the New York Times as an
organization it's incredible and he he's
a sole practitioner for Bloomberg he's
the one who broke the uh the Hillary
Clinton email story based solely on Foya
so Jason leapold
requested on a slow day one day he had
nothing else to do so he thought I'm
just gonna I'm gonna do a foyer request
the CIA for all correspondence between
the cia's office of public affairs and
any national security journalist okay
most of it was garbage but what he found
was a series of emails between kend
delanian and the CIA where kend delanian
was sending his stories to the CIA for
clearance before he was sending them to
his own
editors and the CIA was saying hey Ken
in par paragraph two uh third sentence
we don't like that take that
out uh in paragraph six we prefer if you
say this or use this language so is kend
delanian reporting on the intelligence
Community or is the intelligence
Community feeding propaganda to kend
delanian for him to repeat on NBC and
MSNBC to the American
people
disgraceful disgraceful another thing
that Jason leapold found in this Freedom
of Information Act request was any time
a journalist was writing something that
the CIA didn't like something that was
not complimentary of the CIA and would
send it to the CIA for comment right
which the CIA never does they never ever
ever have a comment um but you have to
do it that's the
protocol they would respond by saying if
you publish this you will be cut off and
you will not be invited to the CIA
Christmas
party
seriously and they would back
off wow so they don't need to recruit
American
journalists there's no reason to recruit
them you control them
anyway you control them by threatening
them on the one hand or by feeding them
the information that you want to leak
Allah kend delanian on the
other um I have a I have a question on
something that you mentioned on on our
bosses Robert Shear's uh podcast not too
long ago people should definitely check
that out um that John Brennan went after
you and threw uh Attorney General Eric
Holder for Espionage charges right um
despite holder's uh hesitant and they
made you defend yourself and essentially
bankrupt yourself in in doing so so do
you read this as a means of making an
example of your of you and you know
despite their you know uh hesitancy to
to really go after this in court um they
still found some sort of way to you know
exploit any Avenue to to destroy you oh
absolutely and and I know that I know
that for two different reasons number
one um a reporter for the New York Times
told
me well a reporter for the New York
Times wrote me a letter in prison and he
said he just felt awful about what had
happened and could he come and visit me
and I said sure I said listen no hard
feelings I'm a big boy I knew what I was
getting into there's nothing that the
New York Times could do to to save me
right so he came to visit me and he said
he wanted to apologize face to face I
said not a problem and he said you know
this was not really about you right and
I saidwell what do you mean and he said
the day that you were arrested every
National Security Source that the New
York Times had went silent for six
months and he said that was the point
the point wasn't a long sentence for
John kiraku he said they didn't care how
long your sentence was the point was to
silence anybody else who might be
considering blowing the whistle on waste
fraud abuse or illegality it was to
frighten everybody look what we did to
this guy we ruined him we drove him to
bankruptcy we confiscated his federal
pension do you want the same thing to
happen to you no then keep your mouth
shut that was number one number two one
of my attorneys my lead attorney said
the same thing he said this case really
isn't about on kiraku this case is about
whistleblowing and it's about the lack
of whistleblower protections for
National Security whistleblowers we have
a whistleblower protection act in the
United States but National Security
employees are exempt from its
protections so if you work for the
Department of Agriculture or the EPA or
the Department of Labor you can blow the
whistle to your heart's content God
bless maybe you're going to be be on the
cover of Time Magazine if you work for
the CIA the NSA FBI DOD you're going to
go straight to prison and you're
probably GNA stay there for quite some
time yeah um and you know when we look
at the if we go back to the intercept
for a second when we look at the
intercepts staff some of some of the
staff like Matthew Cole and Richard
espacito
and you and when you think of Pierro
midar who's you know a huge funer of
regime change operations for the
National Security State and knowing what
Matthew Cole did to you and what Richard
Esposito's uh association with um the
police right and uh you know like when
you think about all these variables um
what does it like you know because there
but there's also some journalists that I
respect at the uh that that were at the
founding of the inter
but
like it's it's kind of a crazy scenario
for me to think about because it's just
such a complex kind of form of uh
information Warfare and a psychological
operation I guess in a way and like if
if that's what it is and and you know
what do you what is your personal
opinion on that if we could if we could
ask like on Pierro M's involvement and
the hiring of these guys that
consistently are ratting on uh their on
on their sources and locking them up um
what does that say about that
institution and the role that it really
was serving maybe from the
beginning you know there was such hope
and such promise when Pier omdar first
announced that he was going to create
something called The Intercept I
remember I remember so many like real
go-getter independent journalists that I
knew and how excited they were to to try
to find work at the inter intercept you
know because this was this was going to
be the first truly well-funded outlet
that was independent of the long arm of
the
CIA and you know it's it's laughable now
in retrospect to look back and to think
that that you know that that there was
even a possibility that that could be
the case uh Pierre omdar of course being
the multi-billionaire founder of
eBay uh had a lot of people fool for a
long time that he was interested in
transparency and honesty and
Independence uh in the media you know
protection of our first amendment rights
for example that was a joke when you're
funding the National Endowment for
democracy uh for example or the Atlantic
Council or the German Marshall fund
you're you're no friend of
transparency you no friend of of peace
or open this in in government it's just
a bad joke and then when the intercept
when The Intercept starts um starts
hiring the likes of of riches bazito and
Matthew Cole who I would add in my
indictment are listed as um journalist a
and journalist
B uh you know you're in trouble you know
when I when I um got home from prison in
2015 I got an invitation from Jeremy
skill the editor-in-chief of of the uh
intercept to go up to New York and to be
on his podcast and I like Jeremy he's a
nice guy I disagree with him on a lot of
things but he's a nice guy so I said yes
I'd be happy to do it I take the train
up to New York and he's waiting for me
at the inter at the intercepts uh
entrance and I go in and I I had met him
several times before so I said Jeremy
before we get started I gotta ask you I
said Matthew [__] Cole are you
kidding me and he goes I know I know you
guys don't see see eye to eye on things
I said no it's not that eye to eye it's
that he's single-handedly responsible
for putting me in a federal
prison that's my beef with Matthew Cole
and I said Rich ESP bazito listen I'm
the first to admit Rich ESP bazito was
my best
friend but Rich ESP bazito always wanted
to be a cop from when he had his first
journalistic assignment as the midnight
shift uh crime blotter cop for the
whatever it was called the New York
Daily
News until he became the Deputy
Commissioner for public affairs he
always wanted to be a cop like those are
the best journalists that you could find
for The Intercept
seriously and he's like well you know
that's just the way it
is like okay next thing you know reality
winner goes to prison
Terry Albury goes to prison Daniel hail
the Drone whistleblower okay let's talk
about Daniel Hae for a second yeah
wasn't that skill that was
skill here you've got a guy who's
telling you top secret information about
the American drone program and how 80%
of the victims of the Drone program are
civilians and most of them are women and
children so this is like top secret
uh targeting
information and Jeremy he skill says Hey
listen uh Daniel uh I'm going to do this
documentary why don't you appear on the
documentary with me and out yourself as
the source of our our stories on on the
Drone program well Daniel never worked
with journalists before he didn't know
any better and so he allows himself to
appear in this documentary next thing
you know the FBI is breaking down his
door putting cuffs on him it's like way
to protect your sources there Jeremy
good
job yeah that's uh that's pretty amazing
um and it's just like it's just like
Source after Source after Source same
story um oh yeah and then Omar's
attachment to it just makes it all the
more suspect um and look at it this way
too how many of these These Guys these
billionaires let's use Jeff Bezos as as
the most obvious example Jeff Bezos
democracy dies in Darkness now it says
on the front page of the Washington Post
which he purchased but he also does $400
million a year in business with a CIA
providing uh classified uh Cloud
space so how how do you separate the two
either you're going to report honestly
about the CIA and the crimes that the
CIA is committing or you're going to
take the cia's blood soaked money and
put it in your pocket because it
shouldn't be both
and it is both is Pierre omard doing the
same thing I don't know but I think it's
a question that he needs to
answer yeah it seems like a lot of these
guys and these intelligence agencies um
have like a false sense of self this re
this uh personality that they kind of
project onto uh or that they project to
convey themselves as these good people
right like uh Bezos is like a liberal
guy that you know has a liberal news
outlet that the slogan is democracy dies
in darkness but then you're a CIA
contractor uh and and that's the part
you don't talk about right it's kind of
reminds me of um like the the big tech
people that do iasa and then they're
working for Palante or something like
that oh my God a
great yeah
yeah it's pretty brilliant um but uh
yeah and and and then the other thing
about the another thing about The
Intercept that is very strange is that
they got a whole of the Snowden archive
and um and then now that they I think
they asked their research Department
right and um which is the which is the
and they said it was for budgetary
reasons which I don't know how true that
is or what but uh either way now the
Snowden archive is in the hands of
Pierro midar this guy that again is
funding regime change operations uh and
works closely with the intelligence
agent gencies and he's the guy that owns
it and no one's looking at it no one's
putting it out there and it's just it's
just um extremely damaging and it was a
pretty you know when you look at it from
the from the perspective of this like
how many whistleblowers it busted how it
privatized the ownership of the Snowden
archive it makes the The Intercept was a
huge success in terms of uh what it was
actually probably meant to do
right and I'll tell you not a day goes
by now that I don't get at least four
fundraising emails from The Intercept
every day every single day like please
just send us five dollar please we can't
make it why because your billionaire
founder won't write you another check I
mean what is
this I I just don't understand their
their business model I don't understand
their ethics and I don't understand if
they've ever really been serious about
their commitment to to True transparent
journalism I highly doubt
it yeah and you you know talking about
this incompetence from these reporters
and stuff I can't help but see the
parallels in in my own experiences uh
with with journalism school you know I
actually study journalism I don't know
about these guys if they actually did
but you know and you've spoken in Bob's
classes at at USC and I I I don't want
to talk too much [__] about my alma moer
but at the same time you know studying
journalism you would expect there to be
some sort of actual teaching of of these
core principles and and including this
kind of thing Source protection all this
kind of stuff and I never I never had
any classes that dealt with that
fascinating and you know I think Bob
Shear would tell you too well I know for
a fact that he would because I've heard
him say it
um the anenberg school of Journalism is
supposed to be one of the the greatest
journalism uh schools in America if not
in the world right right they're not
teaching you journalistic ethics and
there should be a standalone class on
journalistic ethics right because
sometimes ethics aren't
clearcut there are there are moral calls
that you need to make um and then this
is the same school that goes and hires
uh David Petraeus of all people to be a
lecturer like not in not a lecturer in
the school of you know whatever military
studies or intelligence Community
studies I'm making those up of course
but in the school of Journalism
seriously you're going to you're going
to name the former director of the
CIA fourstar General who who is a
convicted criminal for lying to the
FBI right cheated on his wife so even
his wife can't trust him I don't know
how the country can trust him and that's
the guy who's going to help teach you
journalism that's just
Grand yeah I guess they were on the
trend of um hiring Spooks to be doing
journalism even before MSNBC and CNN
right
exactly yeah you say something Diego
sorry yeah I think I think it just lends
itself to a general erosion of ethics
and and I think it is purposeful in a
way where you have people like uh Ken uh
delanian right and and all these people
who you know I I mean I don't know
what's what's going on in his brain but
I'm sure all these kind of reporters at
the New York Times or whatever who
accept information from direct uh
officials they probably think they're
doing the right thing they probably
think they're they're helping their
country and they're reporting as
honestly as they can in the name of uh
combating disinformation all all these
kind of things that get in the way of of
actual truth you know and it's it's yeah
it just I think what happened at the
intercept and what continues to happen
to whistleblowers is
just a perfect case study of of how
Journal is just going down the
drain I I would agree with that very
strongly and I would also agree with you
very strongly that this is something
that needs to be addressed at places
like USC or Colombia or Georgetown or
Princeton where where schools are
turning
out young journalists who are going to
be the future of
Journalism you know you've got to have
this in instilled in you from the very
beginning because listen it's the same
thing W with the CIA joining the CIA
you're not going to be taught ethics at
the CIA you have to go into your CIA
career with your own ethical principles
already in place your own
moral uh moral guidelines a part of your
life you know I have this standard
speech that I give uh at
universities and I use a high
hypothetical
situation and I say imagine you are a
CIA case officer and you've recruited a
Bonafide terrorist let's say a member of
al-Qaeda or Isis or Hezbollah a true
terrorist and this guy has given you
information that is gold and you've used
this information to disrupt terrorist
attacks and to save American lives okay
so you're going to meet with him at a
hotel somewhere in the Middle East
wherever you want Aman Cairo wherever
and you go into the meeting and he says
to you you know what I've been good to
you and I've given you everything you
asked for and so tonight you're going to
do something for me I'm not going to
give you any more information until you
get me a
prostitute so do you get him the
prostitute yes or no and I ask for a
show of hands and usually about 75% of
the hands go up and I say yes you get
him the prostitute you know this is kind
of the the ugly part of the job but this
is what you're trained to do you need to
make your Source happy keep your Source
happy so that he continues to give you
information so yes it might be um you
know not the nicest thing you've ever
done but you would get the guy a
prostitute I said what if he asks you
for a child
prostitute then what do you
do and you usually people kind of look
around and maybe 10% of the hands will
gingerly go up and then I say
absolutely
not absolutely not you have to draw the
line somewhere but the thing is you're
not going to be taught this at the CIA
you have to go in there with a sense of
right and wrong and you tell this guy I
will not be party to a child crime I
will not do it I will not victimize a
child for you if you don't want to work
with me anymore then you don't have to
work with me anymore I think that we
have this relationship because we're
saving lives and I'm paying you
handsomely but I'm not going to
victimize a child for you again the
point
being headquarters isn't going to tell
you what to do right the desk that's
following your operations they're not
going to tell you what to do and there's
no written rule where you can look into
the CIA rule book can say oh now rule
number 16.3 point1 says no I can't get
you a child prostitute that's that's not
that's not real life it's not how it
works well it's the same thing in
journalism you have to go into this with
your own set of moral values your own
ethical
construct that's that's already a part
of you you know a an Israeli
psychologist uh and author once told me
he he wrote a book about whistleblowing
called uh Souls his name is Al press he
said one of the things that he found in
Psychology was that whistleblowers have
a an unusually highly defined sense of
right and wrong far more highly defined
than the uh than the general public but
the same is true among
journalists now sometimes those
journalists lose their sense of right
and wrong in pursuit of a story or even
worse in pursuit of a
relationship with an organization like
the CIA
and the key then is is not to lose that
sense of right and
wrong yeah and you know about how that
uh that emphasizing that is completely
absent in any journalism school I mean
one of the things that Diego and I used
to talk about when we were at USC um a
lot and we still talk about it sometimes
was that no one in our school and I'm
not exaggerating like I I think I maybe
met like one one or two people that knew
who Julian Assange was at apparently the
best journalism School in the in the
world I or the country I don't remember
what they say it is but um no one knew
and no one really cared either and uh I
remember like the one so we were having
a discussion in class one time and I
think that this kind of encapsulates
like that theme that you were talking
about of like you know do you let your
sense of what's right and wrong guide
the kind of reporting that you do or
some other kind of external factor and
the conversation was about um there were
these I guess there was these guys that
in in World War II Germany reported on
like the crimes of the of the uh Nazi
soldiers um and not that many people
read it because it was extremely
censored and uh and the the the
professor asked us something like uh you
know is it worth it to do this kind kind
of like courageous reporting if people
aren't going to read it because you know
power will not permit it to be read and
I said and I raised my hand and I said
yeah absolutely I mean like you know for
the sake of the historical record and
also for the sake of like being Guided
by what you believe is newsworthy and
important for people to read even if
you're fighting an uphill battle to get
people to read it it is important and I
said and I said you know I think that
one example of a reporter that has done
some courageous reporting that many
people don't know about now because of
his courageous reporting and because of
how much he's been censored and smeared
by the mainstream media and the
political class is Julian Assange and
without him we wouldn't know yeah we
wouldn't know all these things about uh
you know the bush crime the Bush's war
crimes in Iraq and how they were bombing
I mean I mean that that that Infamous
footage where they bomb these guys this
group of civilians and then they kill
the First Responders while there were
children in the van
collateral yeah and just to and just to
and just to demonstrate how unconcerned
journalism School professors are with
that kind of thinking the the professor
told me well it's hard for me to really
care what happens to Julian Assange
because he's so damn unlikable
yeah he is listen I know Julian very
very well um and he can be difficult and
unlikable and that is utterly irrelevant
to the situation
I was on a panel about a year ago with
uh with two former journalists from
night Ritter and a member of the
audience asked them why they and other
members of the mainstream media
especially the the post the times and
the journal would not come out in in
defense of Julian Assange and without
missing a beat one of these journalists
said I don't consider Julian Assange to
be a journalist I consider him to be an
activist and the the audience members
said but the post the times the journal
and everybody else um have based
articles on Julian assange's information
and so even if you don't consider him to
be a journalist you have to acknowledge
that he's at least a
publisher and they were like next
question
please that was it that was the end of
it it was
shocking yeah yeah crazy crazy Diego do
you have another question before we do
the last question uh no I think I think
that's a good segue um to get into
that okay yeah so um
so uh Diego and I have been having these
discussions uh lately about truth and
the value of truth and you
know uh what like at the Times the
people you know hold it back and also uh
talking about journalists and like when
you know maybe people hold back the
truth on some issue that they know is
controversial so that they can talk
about another TR to the truth about
another issue later and this kind of
like constant battle that we're fighting
between um authenticity and risking
ourselves in the process and I think
that like whistleblowers are such a
great um example of this kind of
like spiritual or physical philosophical
kind of battle that I think that humans
are facing especially in the fields in
the field of Journalism and um you know
like there's this I I write fiction a
lot and there's this saying uh that a
character doesn't change until it
becomes less painful for him to change
than to remain the same and I think that
the interesting yes yeah and I think
that the true it's also true of of real
people not just characters and um I I
wanted to ask you like you know like
yourself and other whistleblowers they
do this thing that's like seemingly kind
of irrational by every measure right you
know once you blow the whistle you're
going to like face serious physical
consequences you might put your loved
ones in danger you're putting yourself
in danger you're putting your career in
danger you're putting every material
attachment that you have on the line
because for some reason it's more I I I
I would think that it's more painful
inside to bear that truth any longer
than to like let it out and to and to
and to just face the consequences so
like you know as someone who blew the
whistle and you seriously paid the price
for it how do you make sense of that
battle like what what point is it that
that becomes more painful than prison or
or all these other consequences that
whistle blind the whistle can put on
someone yeah yeah you know I never
considered myself ever in my life over
the course of my life I never considered
myself as a as a boat rocker never um
even at the CIA I did what I was told
and I did it with a smile on my face
until it came to the post 911 era and
human rights
abuses these these um programs whether
it was torture or secret prisons or
extraordinary
Renditions were so obviously
wrong like I couldn't see any
upside over the long
term to doing any of these these things
these were so obviously crimes against
humanity that I remember thinking to
myself are my children and grandchildren
going to be proud of me I mean there
there are Generations that haven't been
born yet grandchildren great
grandchildren you know when I'm dead and
gone are they going to be proud of me
and what I
did I want to leave a legacy for them
you know I'm I'm proud of the of the
people that my parents were and my
grandparents I'm proud of them and they
were just working people you know they
never really did anything that was
historically noteworthy but they were
good people good moral ethical
upstanding people and I'm proud of them
and I want my kids and grandchildren to
be proud of me now I found myself at the
CIA in this historic
situation so it's not just like oh was
Dad a good guy yeah dad was a good guy
he was always honest and he was kind to
you know strangers and the poor and
children and and small
animals was I kind to people who were
accused of committing
terrorism maybe that's not the right
question maybe the question is was I
true to the Constitution was I true to
the oath that I took on my first day in
the CIA when I raised my right hand and
I swore to uphold and protect and defend
the Constitution of the United States
against all enemies foreign and
domestic I hate to think that in the
room that day I was the only one of the
300 who took that oath who actually
meant
it but I thought you know this is going
this is this is going to be a life
decision and I've got to do the right
thing to tell you the truth I I barely
remember being in prison it was just
such a a short little uh period of my
life it was 23 easy months it was a
decade ago I don't even think about it
anymore um but I can sleep at night and
my kids are proud of me and I'll tell
you a follow on to that my my third son
just started college last month as a
freshman and he called me on his first
day of class and he was very excited and
he said dad you're never going to
believe I just walked out of my first e
ever ethics
class and I interrupted him and I was
like ah I hated my ethics class it was
all philosophy and these German
philosophers I never heard of and ever
cared about and he's like no no no wait
a minute he said I'm telling you I just
walked out of my first ever ethics class
and the professor was talking about
ethics in
Wartime and he said there are 300 kids
in this class it's in this giant
Auditorium and the professor said
there's this guy John kiraku he was with
the CIA and he couldn't remain silent
when he saw the torture program and he
went to prison because he blew the
whistle on it and he Saidi wanted to
shout that's my dad
and I said you see Max his my son's name
is Max too I said you see it's all worth
it it's all worth it that made it worth
it you know yeah the the night before I
went to
prison uh Jose Rodriguez the former
deputy director of the CIA tweeted at
me and all he said was um don't drop the
soap
[__] and I gave myself a few hours to
calm down take it easy and I tweeted
back and I said hose I am on the right
side of history and you are
not and I left it at that now here we
are 12 years later
almost
and he's going to go down in
history as a torturer as a murderer when
his obituary is written it's going to
say that he was the Godfather of the
torture program he murdered un told
people innocent people he ordered
innocent people to be kidnapped and sent
to third countries to be tortured there
some of them never made it out
alive I'd rather be John kiraku than to
be that
guy yeah me
too me
three well um uh did you want to ask
another question Max no no uh I think
that's a great place to wrap it up
unless you had something to say to you
go uh no yeah no that was that was
amazing thank you John so much for for
coming on and talking thank you guys
listen these were these were among the
best questions anybody has asked me in
one setting
Kudos that means a lot coming from you
thank you thank you
absolutely great good to see you both
good to see
you
[Music]